<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Question 1</title>
        <author ref="#Bonaventure">Bonaventure</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JW">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Question 1</title>
          <date when="2025-12-18">December 12, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
          
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Qb" n="Quaracchi1885">Quaracchi 1885, Volume 2</witness>
          <witness xml:id="H" n="harv265">Harvard, lat ms. 265</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a critical edition.</p>
        
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-18" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
          
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1">
        <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Hd1e108">Question 1</head>
        
        <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Hd1e111" type="question-title">Whether Christians are bound to be subject to tyrants or secular power in certain matters.</head>
        
        <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e114">Concerning the first,
          we proceed as follows and ask whether Christians are bound to be subject to tyrants or secular power in certain matters.</p>
        
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Dd1e117" type="rationes-principales">
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e119">And that they are seems clear:
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e116" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e121">1 Peter 2:18</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e121" source="http://scta.info/resource/Ipetr2_18@1-14">Servants,
              be subject to your masters with all fear,
              not only to the good and gentle,
              but also to the harsh</quote>.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e125">Again,
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e124" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e127">Romans 13:1</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e127" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1">Let every soul be subject to higher powers</quote>;
            and after:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e130" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_7">Render therefore to all their dues:
              tribute to whom tribute is due,
              custom to whom custom</quote>.
            And if you say that this is an admonition for the sake of avoiding scandal;
            on the contrary,
            a little before:
            You must be subject by necessity,
            not only because of wrath but also for conscience's sake.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e134">Again,
            this very thing is shown by the reasoning that the Apostle makes there.
            He says,
            there is no power except from God;
            but those things which are from God are ordained;
            therefore every power is ordained by divine ordinance:
            thus whoever resists the power resists God's ordinance;
            but whoever resists God's ordinance acquires damnation for himself:
            therefore etc.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e137">Again,
            to serve man is not a fault or evil,
            but rather meritorious:
            therefore it seems that one is not absolved from that servitude through baptism:
            therefore just as non-Christians are servants of others,
            so even if they become Christians,
            they are bound to serve.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e140">Again,
            for this same point there are many authorities,
            which can be taken from almost all the Epistles of blessed Paul,
            in which he admonishes servants to be subject to their masters.</p>
          
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e144">But to the contrary:
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e147" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e146">Matthew 17:24</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e146" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt17_24">From whom do the kings of the earth receive tribute?
              From their own sons,
              or from strangers?</quote>
            and after,
            below:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e149" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt17_25">Therefore the sons are free</quote>;
            and the Gloss there:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e152">The sons of the kingdom are free in every kingdom,
              much more are the sons of that kingdom free,
              under which are all kingdoms,
              in any earthly kingdom</quote>.
            If therefore good Christians are sons of that kingdom,
            it seems that they are not bound under the power of any earthly king:
            therefore they are not bound to be subject to him in any tribute.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e156">Again,
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e161" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e158">James 1:25</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e158" source="http://scta.info/resource/iac1_25">But whoever has looked into the law of perfect liberty</quote>,
            the Gloss explains that
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e161">the law of perfect liberty is the Gospel law</quote>.
            Therefore,
            if perfect liberty liberates from all servitude,
            it seems that everyone who adheres to the law of the Gospel is absolved from all servitude to an earthly king.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e165">Again,
            charity makes all members of Christ one and makes all things common;
            hence
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e166" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e167">1 Corinthians 3:22</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e167" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor3_22">All things are yours,
              whether death or life</quote>
            etc.
            It makes all things one,
            because the
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e171">Apostle says both to the Ephesians</ref>
            and
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e173">to the Colossians</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e170">We are all one in Christ,
              and there is no distinction between servant and free</quote>.
            Therefore,
            if charity reduces all members to equality and community,
            it seems therefore that in those having charity there is no obligation of servitude.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e174">Again,
            the bond of divine law is greater than the bond of human constitution;
            but the Gospel law absolves from the burden of legal servitude,
            which indeed had been established by God through Moses:
            therefore much more strongly it absolves from the burden of human servitude and civil law.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e177">Again,
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e189" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e179">Anselm,
              in the book Why God Became Man,
              chapter five</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e179">He wished to redeem by himself,
              so that he might restore man to his original liberty,
              and man might be subject to himself,
              not to man</quote>.
            If therefore we have been bought with a great price,
            namely the blood of the undefiled and immaculate lamb,
            it seems that we are servants of him alone:
            therefore it does not seem that a Christian man,
            who has been reborn in Christ,
            is bound to any servitude of earthly empire.</p>
          
        </div>
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Dd1e184">
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Hd1e186">Conclusion</head>
          
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Hd1e189" type="question-title">Christians are obligated to earthly masters,
            but not in all things,
            but only in those things which are not against God,
            and which have been reasonably established according to right custom.</head>
          
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e192">I respond:
            It must be said that,
            since servitude is opposed to liberty,
            according as liberty is said to be threefold,
            namely from compulsion and from fault and from misery,
            so servitude can be called threefold,
            which is observed in the restriction of liberty.
            For according to the restriction of liberty from fault is observed the servitude of sin,
            concerning which
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e199" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e201">John 8:34</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e201" source="http://scta.info/resource/io8_34@10-15">Whoever commits sin is a servant of sin</quote>;
            and
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e204" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e206">Romans 6:12</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e206" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom6_12@1-8">Let not sin reign in your mortal body</quote>.
            But according to the restriction of liberty from misery is observed the servitude of punishment and death,
            concerning which it is said
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e209" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e212">Romans 6:9</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e212" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom6_9@3-14">Christ rising from the dead now dies no more,
              death shall no longer have dominion over him</quote>.
            But according to the restriction of liberty from compulsion is observed the servitude of condition,
            concerning which it is said
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e215" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e217">1 Corinthians 7:21</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e217" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor7_21@1-15">Were you called as a servant?
              Care not for it;
              but if you can become free,
              rather use it</quote>.
            But this servitude is observed in the restriction of liberty from compulsion,
            not as regards the interior movement of the will,
            which cannot be compelled,
            but as regards the exterior.
            Hence servitude was also introduced in this,
            that one conquered another and subjected him to his servitude,
            so that it is not permitted to do the contrary of what he himself has commanded.</p>
          
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e195">Since therefore servitude is threefold,
            one has its origin from another;
            for there would not be servitude of punishment unless servitude of fault had preceded;
            nor would servitude of condition follow unless that twofold servitude preceded.
            When therefore someone is regenerated in Christ and becomes a Christian,
            he is liberated from the servitude of sin;
            but nevertheless he is not so liberated that he does not also have the possibility and facility and proneness to return to the same kind of servitude;
            and hence it is that for his advancement and humiliation the Lord leaves to him the servitude of death and condition.
            Hence Christians die just as others do;
            and because of their proneness to evil and the concupiscences warring in their members,
            from which arise wars and disputes,
            they need to be ruled by an earthly prince just as other peoples do -
            and therefore not only according to human institution,
            but also according to divine dispensation among Christians there are kings and princes,
            masters and servants -
            and according to the distinction of power they are subject to them and bound according to more and less.
            And this the Lord himself says,
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e223" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e225">Matthew 22:21</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e225" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt22_21@8-17">Render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's,
              and to God the things that are God's</quote>.
            And the
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e228">Apostle,
              1 Timothy 6:3</ref>
            teaches this and condemns those preaching the contrary.
            For he says thus:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e230" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@1-17">Whoever are under the yoke of servitude should consider their masters worthy of all honor,
              lest the name of the Lord and his teaching be blasphemed</quote>.
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e233" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_3@1-20 http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_4@1-3">But if anyone teaches otherwise and does not consent to the sound words of our Lord Jesus Christ,
              he is proud,
              knowing nothing</quote>
            etc.
            And he proves this same thing to the Romans,
            and in many other places he teaches and commands it.
            And therefore it must be conceded that Christians are obligated to earthly masters,
            not however in all things,
            but only in those things which are not against God;
            nor in all of these,
            but in those things which have been reasonably established according to right custom,
            such as tributes and taxes and similar things.
            Hence the authorities and reasons which prove this are to be conceded.</p>
          
        </div>
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Dd1e200">
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Hd1e202">To the arguments</head>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e205">To that therefore which is first objected from the text and
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e246">Gloss,
              Matthew 17:24</ref>,
            it must be said that the text understands this concerning Christ,
            that Christ was not bound to pay tribute,
            and concerning those who are his perfect imitators,
            such as the Apostles,
            because they were naturally free and had left behind all temporal goods;
            and therefore the kings of the earth ought not to receive census or tribute from them.
            But in other Christians,
            either who are of servile condition or who abound in temporal goods,
            that authority must not be understood.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e208">To that which is objected,
            that the Gospel law is the law of perfect liberty,
            it must be said that it is therefore called the law of perfect liberty because it liberates from the servitude of transgression,
            or even from the servitude of the Law,
            while in it is given the spirit of charity,
            which is the spirit of liberty,
            according to what the
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e251" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e253">Apostle says in Romans 8:15</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e253" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom8_15@1-13">You have not received the spirit of servitude again in fear,
              but the spirit of adoption as sons</quote>.
            And therefore it does not follow from this that a man who is under the Gospel law is liberated from the servitude of earthly dominion.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e211">To that which is objected,
            that charity unites all and makes things common,
            it must be said that this is true through a certain participation,
            but it is not true through the authority of dominion.
            It also unites all,
            but this is according to affection,
            not according to the indistinction of rank and dignity;
            for in the body of Christ there is great distinction of members,
            although as regards conformity of affections there is great union.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e214">To that which is objected,
            that the Gospel law absolves from the burden of the Mosaic law,
            therefore much more strongly from human law,
            it must be said that it is not similar,
            because this law fulfills and empties that law as truth empties figure.
            But it is not thus concerning the law of human institution,
            which greatly aids in the observance of divine law.
            Hence the Apostle commands that prayers be made for princes,
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e262">1 Timothy 2:2</ref>,
            that we may lead a quiet and tranquil life under them.</p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-d1e218">To that which is objected,
            that Christ wished to redeem by himself in order to restore to original liberty,
            it must be said that there is noted the full effect of redemption made by Christ.
            But nevertheless we do not fully attain that effect in the present,
            while the creature groans and labors,
            until it is liberated from the servitude of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the sons of God.
            Hence here liberty from fault is begun,
            but there liberty from misery and from all human power will be consummated.
            Hence it does not follow that,
            if we have been bought by Christ,
            that on account of this we are not servants of another,
            because the dominion of Christ well tolerates with itself the dominion of man,
            especially in those things where they command nothing against God;
            but it does not tolerate with itself the dominion of the devil or sin,
            according to that
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Rd1e268" corresp="#bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e270">Matthew 6:24</ref>:
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a3q1-Qd1e270" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt6_24@1-5">You cannot serve two masters</quote>.
            Therefore,
            although by the redemption of Christ we are rescued from the servitude of mortal sin,
            nevertheless we are not rescued from the servitude of condition or death.</p>
          
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>