<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Question 2</title>
        <author ref="#Bonaventure">Bonaventure</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JW">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Question 2</title>
          <date when="2025-12-18">December 18, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
            
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Qb" n="Quaracchi1885">Quaracchi 1885, Volume 2</witness>
          <witness xml:id="H" n="harv265">Harvard, lat ms. 265</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a critical edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-18" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2">
        <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e108">Question 2</head>
        <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e111" type="question-title">
          Whether the power of ruling is in man according to the institution of nature 
          or according to the punishment of sin.
        </head>
        <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e114">
          Second, it is asked concerning this, 
          whether the power of ruling is in man according to the institution of nature 
          or according to the punishment of sin.
        </p>
        
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Dd1e117" type="rationes-principales">
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e119">Principal Arguments</head>
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e122">
            And that it is in the first way, it seems: 
            Genesis 1:26: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e124" source="http://scta.info/resource/gen1_26">Let us make man in our image and likeness, 
              and let him rule</quote>
            etc. 
            If you say that he had dominion over the beasts but not over men, 
            one does not escape through this, 
            because 1 Corinthians 11:3: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e127" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor11_3">The man is the head of the woman</quote>.
            
            Therefore if the head rules the body and ought to govern the body, 
            therefore it seems that according to the institution of nature 
            there is the power of dominating in the human race.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e131">
            Likewise, in the angels who are perfect in nature and in glory, 
            there is not only order and rank according to the excellence of natural gifts, 
            but also according to the ruling of offices: 
            therefore it seems that dominion does not conflict with, 
            but rather harmonizes with the institution of human nature 
            just as with angelic nature.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e134">
            Likewise, the power of dominating is a property of dignity and nobility; 
            but if any dignity belongs to fallen nature, 
            much more does it belong to instituted nature: 
            therefore it seems that the power of dominating pertained more 
            to the state of instituted nature than to the state of fallen nature.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e137">
            Likewise, everything that is for the conservation of the natural order 
            pertains to the institution of nature; 
            but the power of ruling pertains to the conservation of the natural order: 
            therefore the power of ruling is in man from God 
            according to the institution of nature. 
            The major premise is manifest. 
            The minor is proved by what 
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Rd1e134"><name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e135" ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> says, 
              in book XIX of the City of God</ref>: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e139" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l19-d1e3134@295-306">Penal servitude is ordained by that law which commands 
              the natural order to be conserved and forbids it to be disturbed</quote>.
            
            But the power of dominating and penal servitude 
            are ordained to the same end: 
            therefore etc.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e144">
            But on the contrary: 
            Gregory: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e146">Nature made all men equal, 
              but for various merits, 
              by the hidden but just dispensation of God, 
              one is set over others</quote>.
            
            Therefore it seems that subjection and rulership 
            are not in man according to the institution of nature.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e150">
            Likewise, 
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Rd1e152"><name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e153" ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, 
              in book XIX of the City of God</ref>: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e155" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l19-d1e3134@24-32">God did not wish rational man, 
              made in the image of God, 
              to have dominion except over irrational things</quote>.
            
            Therefore, 
            if the power of ruling and dominating is in one man with respect to another, 
            it seems etc.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e159">
            Likewise, this very thing seems evident by reason. 
            Freedom is in man from nature; 
            but the power of dominating is an impediment to freedom: 
            therefore it does not seem that it is from nature. 
            But that freedom is both from nature 
            and has an impediment from the power of ruling is made manifest, 
            because freedom is defined thus: 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e161">Freedom is a natural power 
              by which it is permitted for a man to do what he wishes</quote>.
            
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e165">
            Likewise, man according to his first condition was made in the image of God; 
            but insofar as he is the image of God, 
            he is born to be borne immediately toward God: 
            therefore, if God alone is greater than him, 
            therefore according to nature nothing is above man except God. 
            Therefore no dominion is in man according to the institution of nature 
            except divine dominion alone.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e168">
            Likewise, there is no lord without a servant, 
            therefore neither dominion without servitude; 
            but 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e170">servitude was introduced on account of sin</quote>,
            
            as 
            <name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e175" ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>
            says in many places: 
            therefore it seems that the power of dominating in man is according to 
            the condition of sin, 
            not according to the institution of nature.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e177">
            Likewise, in the glorification of men 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e179" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l22-d1e3726@83-86">vices will be taken away 
              and nature will be preserved</quote>,
            
            according to what 
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Rd1e184"><name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e186" ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> 
              maintains in the book on the City of God</ref>; 
            but in the state of glory the dominion of rulership 
            and the subjection of servitude will not remain: 
            therefore these do not seem to be in human nature according as it was instituted, 
            but only according as it is fallen and corrupted.
          </p>
          
        </div>
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Dd1e187">
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e189">Conclusion</head>
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e192" type="question-title">
            The power of dominating, 
            insofar as it means the power of coercing subjects, 
            is in man only according to the state of fallen nature
          </head>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e195">
            I respond: 
            It must be said that the power of dominating or ruling is said in three ways, 
            namely most broadly and commonly and properly. 
            Most broadly the power of dominating is said with respect to every thing 
            which man can use according to his pleasure and will; 
            and in this way man is said to be lord of his possessions, 
            whether movable or immovable. 
            In another way the power of dominating or ruling 
            means an excellence of power in commanding him 
            who is capable of reason and precept. 
            In a third way the power of dominating is called 
            the power of coercing subjects; 
            and this power signifies a certain restriction of freedom; 
            and such power of dominating is properly called dominion, 
            to which servitude corresponds.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e198">
            In the first way the power of dominating is common to every state, 
            namely the state of instituted nature and of fallen nature and of glorified nature; 
            and it was in the state of instituted nature in a more excellent way 
            than it is in the state of fallen nature.
            In the second way it belongs to the state of pilgrimage, 
            whether for the state of instituted nature or for the state of fallen nature. 
            For if man had stood, 
            both the man could have commanded the wife 
            and the father could have commanded the son. 
            And this is also found in the angels, 
            as long as they are ministering spirits, 
            because from that aspect they are in some way in the state of pilgrimage. 
            Nevertheless this ruling will not remain in glory, 
            as was shown in the preceding questions.
            But in the third way the power of dominating in man 
            is only according to the state of fallen nature; 
            for it is in him according to the punishment of sin, 
            not according to the institution of nature, 
            and this because the servitude corresponding to it, 
            according to what the Saints say, 
            is the penalty of sin.
            And because we speak here of the power of dominating in this way, 
            therefore the arguments showing that such power is not in man 
            according to his primary condition or according to the state of instituted nature 
            must be conceded.
          </p>
          
        </div>
        <div xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Dd1e203">
          <head xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Hd1e205">Responses to the Arguments</head>
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e208">
            To that therefore which is objected to the contrary 
            from the text of Genesis and from Corinthians, 
            the response is already clear; 
            for they proceed concerning the power of ruling 
            accepted in the first and second ways, 
            not the third. 
            For although the woman is in some way inferior to the man 
            on account of her weaker sex, 
            nevertheless, because she was not created to be a help to him as a servant, 
            but as a companion, 
            hence it is that, 
            although he is called her head, 
            nevertheless he is not called her lord, 
            because she is not his servant. 
            And therefore above 
            <ref xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Rd1e214"><name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e215" ref="#Lombard">the Master</name> 
              said, in distinction eighteen</ref>,
            
            that woman was created for equality; 
            therefore she was formed from the side, 
            not from the feet or from the head, 
            so that she might seem to be the man's companion, 
            not mistress or servant.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e214">
            To that which is objected, 
            that there is rulership in the angels, 
            the response is already clear, 
            because although one rules over another 
            and commands another 
            and has authority over another to command him something 
            that pertains to the office of ministry, 
            nevertheless one angel is not called the servant of another angel; 
            and therefore from this it is not concluded 
            that the power of dominating, 
            according as servitude corresponds to it, 
            is in man according to the condition of nature.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e217">
            To that which is objected, 
            that dominion is a property of dignity, 
            it must be said that although it is a property of dignity 
            in him who rules, 
            nevertheless it signifies unworthiness in him who is subject; 
            and therefore it can naturally belong to man 
            with respect to another inferior creature, 
            but with respect to another man it does not belong naturally, 
            but in a certain way contrary to nature, 
            namely in punishment of sin; 
            just as 
            <name xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Nd1e225" ref="#Ambrose">Ambrose</name>
            says, 
            <quote xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-Qd1e222">servitude was introduced through the sin of drunkenness</quote>.
            
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="bb-l2d44a2q2-d1e226">
            To that which is objected, 
            that dominion and servitude make for the conservation of the natural order, 
            it must be said that there is an order which regards nature according to every state 
            and there is an order which regards nature according to the state of its condition 
            and there is an order which regards nature according to the state of its corruption. 
            And according to this some things are of the dictate of nature simply, 
            some of the dictate of nature according to the state of instituted nature, 
            some of the dictate of nature according to the state of fallen nature. 
            That God is to be honored, 
            nature dictates according to every state; 
            that all things are to be common, 
            it dictates according to the state of instituted nature; 
            that something is to be proper, 
            it dictates according to the state of fallen nature 
            to remove contentions and quarrels. 
            Thus that all men are to be servants of God, 
            nature dictates according to every state; 
            but that man is to be equal to man, 
            it dictates according to the state of his first condition; 
            but that man is to be subject to man 
            and man is to serve man, 
            it dictates according to the state of corruption, 
            so that evil men may be restrained and good men may be defended. 
            For unless there were such dominions coercing the wicked, 
            on account of the corruption which is in nature 
            one would oppress another 
            and men could not live together. 
            But it would not be thus if man had remained in the state of innocence; 
            for each would remain in his rank and state. 
            And thus it is clear that this argument does not conclude 
            that servitude or dominion regards instituted nature, 
            but only that it regards fallen nature, 
            where order can be disturbed and can be conserved through dominion.
          </p>
          
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>